A Guide to the Edward Wren Hudgins Papers, 1899-1958
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Edward Wren Hudgins Papers, 1899-1958
Library of Virginia
34476, 34711
9.9 cubic feet (22 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 34476 - Gift of Brenda Duke, The Fine Arts Museum of Southern Virginia, Chase City, Virginia, 22 July 1993; Accession 34711 - Gift of Brenda Duke, The Fine Arts Museum of Southern Virginia, Chase City, Virginia, 25 January 1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
Edward Wren Hudgins was born in Buckingham County, Virginia on 17 January 1882. He received his B. A. (1905) and LL.B (1908) from Richmond College (now the University of Richmond). He was a member of the Virginia House of Delegates (1916-1920), judge, 34th Judicial Circuit, Virginia (1926-1930), justice, Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia (1930-1947), and chief justice (1947-1958). He died at his home in Chase City, Virginia on 29 July 1958.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1899-1958 (bulk 1948-1958), of Edward Wren Hudgins, former chief justice of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, including correspondence and subject files. Principal correspondents include Hubert D. Bennett, Archibald C. Buchanan, John W. Eggleston, Willis D. Miller, A. Willis Robertson, Lemuel F. Smith, C. Vernon Spratley, Howard G. Turner, and Kennon C. Whittle. Topics covered include Hudgins' work on the Conference of Chief Justices, Judicial Conference of Virginia, and Judicial Council of Virginia, his court opinions, materials concerning judicial administration, ethics, salaries, habeas corpus, and rules of court, personal and official correspondence, income tax returns, clippings, and speeches.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Edward Wren Hudgins Papers, 1899-1958., Extent: 9.9 cu. ft. (22 boxes).
  - "A" - Miscellaneous, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folders 1-2)
  - Admission of Attorneys, October 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Admission of the Bar, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Almond v. Day, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - American Bar Association, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Attorney's Kin to Judge, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Attorneys - Statutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Automobile, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "B" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bennett, Gordon - Marsh, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bennett, Hubert D. 1954-1958 (Box 1-2)
    - Reports, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folders 1-4)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 2, Folders 5-6)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folders 7-10)
  - Bills Paid, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Boatwright, F. W., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mr. Justice Buchanan, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Judge A. C. Buchanan, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Justice Buchanan - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Budget Bill, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "C" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chief Justice's "File Opinions," January 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chief Justice's Opinions - Copies, March-June 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
    - March 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - April 1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - June 1957 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chief Justice's "File" Opinions, September-November 1957, March-April, June, September 1958 (Box 3, Folder 11-17)
    - September 1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - October 1957 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - November 1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - March 1958 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - April 1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - June 1958 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - September 1958 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Class of 1905 History, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1930-1956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1958 (Accession 34711) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Colonial Williamsburg, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Commission to Select Memorial to Chief Justice John Marshall, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia v. Ballou, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Conference of Chief Justices, 1950, 1954-1958 (Box 4-5)
    - 1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1954 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - 1956 (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
    - 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1958 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Corporation Commission Procedure for Reinstatement of Driving License, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Court Matters, 1927-1936 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Court Matters, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "D" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Deeds, 1913-1940 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Dickinson, Charles W., Jr., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "E' - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Edward & Billy - Oil, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Eggleston, Justice John W., 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Justice Eggleston - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Eighteenth Judicial Circuit, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Ellis, Pierce S., 1956 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Estes Express Lines, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Executive Secretary, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - "F" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - February Session, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - First National Bank v. Claiborne, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Football Team (1901-1905), 1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fork Union Military Academy, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "G" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Garden, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Goodman, Mrs. Mabel H., 1953-1958 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "H" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Habeas Corpus, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 10-13)
  - Huckle, V. V., 1955 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Hudgins, Edward M. 1936-1958 (Box 6-7)
    - 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Timber, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - 20 acres of land in Lunenburg, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Personal, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Personal, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Personal, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Wills, 1936-1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Hudgins, Lucy M., 1956 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Hudgins, Lucy M. - Deeds, 1928-1946 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Hudgins, R. B. 1950-1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Hudgins, William H. - General File, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "I" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Income Tax, 1947-1955, 1958 (Box 7-8)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 1949 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - 1950 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - 1951 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - 1952 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - 1953 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - 1954 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - 1955 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1958 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Instructions to Juries, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Insurance Receipts, 1922-1955 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - "J" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1957 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - January Session, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - James, E. Ralph, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Judges' Retirement Bill, 1942, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Judges - Vacancies, 1950-1957 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Judicature Society, 1954-1957 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Judicial Administrator, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Judicial Administrator, 1949-1950 (Box 9, Folder 1-7)
  - Judicial Conference of Virginia, 1950-1958, undated (Box 9-11)
    - 1950 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 1950 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1951 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1952 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1953 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1954 (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
    - 1955 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - 1956 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
    - 1957 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
    - 1958 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
    - Constitution, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Judicial Council, 1929, 1948-1958, undated (Box 11-14)
    - 1929 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1948 (Box 11, Folder 8-10)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Meeting, 3 December 1948 (Box 12, Folder 3-5)
    - Resolutions, etc., 1949 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
    - 1952 (Box 12, Folder 8-11)
    - 1953 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1954 (Box 13, Folder 2-5)
    - 1955 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
    - May 1958 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, 1949-1953 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Judicial Ethics, 1955-1958 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Judicial Ethics, Committee on, 1950-1955 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
  - Judicial Salaries, 1940-1955 (Box 14, Folder 7-8)
  - Judicial Salaries, 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 7-8)
  - Judicial Salaries, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - "K" - Miscellaneous, 1951-1956 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - King v. Beale - Arbitration, 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 12-13)
  - "L" - Miscellaneous, 1951-1958 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Law Library, 1935-1947 (Box 15, Folder 2-4)
  - Law Library - Staunton, 1953-1954 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Law Library Building, 1938-1940 (Box 15, Folder 6-9)
  - Letters - Complimentary, 1949-1957 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Letters of Congratulations, Condolence, Sickness, etc., 1954-1957 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Libraries - Mecklenburg County, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Lowell Bank of St. Louis v. Iona Drainage District, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Lunenburg County Property, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - "M" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Mary Washington College, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - "McC" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1956 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - McCall, Leland Victor, 1957-1958 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda and Opinions - February-March Session, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda - September Session, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
  - Memoranda on Cases, 1954-1956 (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
  - Memos to Secretaries, 1947-1958 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Milk Commission, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Miller, Justice Willis D., 1954-1956 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Justice Miller - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1918-1958 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1899-1958 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Morton, Dr. Heber J. & Mary, 1954-1955 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Morton Land - 50 acres, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Mount Zion Baptist Church - History of, 1947-1957 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - "N" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Naim v. Naim, 1955-1956 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Naim v. Naim - Record No. 4368, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - New Supreme Court Dedication Speech Information, 1940-1941 (Box 17, Folder 4-6)
  - Norfolk County Investigation - Judge A. B. Carney, 1944 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Cases for, 1956 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Notes on Law Cases, 1951-1952 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - "O" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1956 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Opinions, 1954-1957, undated (Box 17-18)
    - 1954 January Session (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - 1954 March Term (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - 1954 April-May Term (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - 1954 June Term (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - 1955 January Session (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - 1955 April Session (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
    - 1955 June Term (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - 1955 September Term (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - 1955 October Session (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - 1955 November Session (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - 1955 Owens v. Owens (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - 1956 February Session - Extra Copies (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - 1956 April Session (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - 1956 April Session - Extra Copies (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - 1956 June Session - Extra Copies (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - 1956 September Session (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - 1956 November Session (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - 1956 November Session - Extra Copies (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - 1957 January Session (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Undated (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - "P" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Judge Parker Memorial, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Pastore, Dr. Peter N., 1958 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Portraits of Justices, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Pre-Trial Conference, 1954-1955 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Printing of Virginia Reports, 1948-1953 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - "R" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Receipts, 1917-1927 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Redick v. Redick, 1913 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Richmond, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Senator A. Willis Robertson, 1956-1958 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Root-Tilden Scholarships, 1952-1957 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Rules of Court, 1945-1957 (Box 19, Folder 13-16)
  - "S" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Segregation, 1955-1958 (Box 20, Folder 2-5)
  - Shackleton Portrait Presentation, 1955 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Smith, Justice Lemuel F., 1954-1957 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Judge Smith - Tax Case, 1957-1958 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1940-1958 (Box 20, Folder 9-12)
  - Spratley, Justice C. Vernon, 1954-1958, undated (Box 21, Folder 1-5)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Speech, 14 June 1958 (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
    - Undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Statistics - by H. G. Turner, 1954-1958 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Statistics - Law Library, 1950-1957 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Staunton, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - "T" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Taxes, 1935 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Tenth Judicial Circuit, 1957 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Thirty-Sixth Judicial Circuit, 1957 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Townsend v. Shackleton, 1914-1915 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Trust Created 9/15/56 - Correspondence - U. S. & State Gift Tax Returns (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Tucker v. Willis, 1901 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - H. G. Turner, 1954-1956 (Box 21, Folder 16-18)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 21, Folder 16-17)
    - Clerk, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Howard G. Turner - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 21, Folder 19-20)
  - Twenty-Ninth Judicial Circuit, 1954-1955 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - "U" - Miscellaneous, 1957 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - U. S. Supreme Court, 1957 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Unemployment Compensation, 1955 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - University of Richmond, 1958 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - University of Richmond Speech on Dr. Boatwright, 1955-1958 (Box 22, Folder 7-8)
  - "V" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1955 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Vaughn, Miss Louise, 1958 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Baptist Foundation, 1956-1958 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Intermont College, 1943 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Virginia State Bar Association, 1954-1958 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - "W" - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Walton v. Walton, 1911 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Watts Land in Lunenburg County, 1942 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Mrs. Alla White, 1948-1952 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - Whittle, Kennon C., 1954-1956 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - Justice Whittle - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - Kennon C. Whittle, 1958 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - "XYZ" - Miscellaneous, 1954 (Box 22, Folder 21)